Hey folks, it is the second day of שלושה ימי הגבלה. Shlosha
Yemei Hagbala. I accidentally said yesterday was that. But anyway, second day,
forty-eighth day of the עומר Omer and I gotta tell you, I
almost forgot to count last night. There was one year, there was
one year I missed on day 49, so anyway.
So
anyway, it's a big deal tomorrow because they're not going to get
done in שול shul before sunset.
I know, yeah, alright. Anyway, דף ה עמוד א, Daf Hey Amud
Aleph, דף ה עמוד א Daf Hey Amud Aleph we start at
the bottom of דף ד עמוד ב. Daf Daled Amud Beis. אמר
רבא, Amar Rava,
first wide line, אמר רבא, Amar Rava, דף ד עמוד ב, Daf
Daled Amud Beis, אמר רבא. Amar Rava. אמר רבא, Amar Rava, מאי
טעמייהו דרבנן? Mai Ta'amaihu DeRabbanan? So we have now presented after a
whole long discussion about the debate of הלל Hillel and שמאי Shammai
and whether you should as when the woman has sees blood now,
how whether you have to be concerned that it happened before, we
have the position of the רבנן Rabbanan which is a middle position,
which is yes you're concerned backwards but not more than 24 hours.
So now the question is, okay, well where does that 24 hours
come from? I mean it's nice that the compromise but what's it
exactly based on? So let's take a look. First wide line on
דף ד עמוד ב. Daf Daled Amud Beis. אמר רבא, Amar Rava,
מאי טעמייהו דרבנן? Mai Ta'amaihu DeRabbanan? What's the reason of the
רבנן? Rabbanan? אשה מרגשת בעצמה. Isha margeshes be'atzma. So the reason is
because a woman would know when she's having her period so we
don't have to wait... I know... so we don't have to wait
all the way back to the last time she checked. So obviously
that sounds like שמאי Shammai and then where's 24 hours come from?
תנא ליה אביי, Tana lei Abaye, אביי Abaye said, אם כן תהא
דיה שעתה, im ken tehei daya sha'ata, so then it should be
enough when she finds the blood, she shouldn't have to be concerned
earlier because she would have felt it. So for רבא, Rava, so
what was so why was רבא Rava saying it? An obvious question.
וכדי לחדודי לאביי הוא דבעי. Uchedei lechaduvei le'Abaye hu deba'ei. He said
right? He was just like testing אביי. Abaye. He was just like,
you know, seeing if אביי Abaye was paying attention. Now you always
wonder exactly what that means, but you know, you know, maybe to
try to encourage אביי Abaye to to say something better, more precise
but you also wonder if it's like an approximate answer that you
know, can you say, well you know, a woman would have felt,
maybe she doesn't realize right away but she would have felt in
the near past. Anyway, the גמרא Gemara you know does not feel
that it's an answer that really should be defended so it says
it was really done just to just to sort of wake up
אביי. Abaye. So let's take a look. רבא Rava was אביי's Abaye
רבי. Rebbi. So אלא, Ella, so now the גמרא Gemara says alright
fine, so what's the real reason? אלא מאי טעמייהו דרבנן? Ella mai
ta'amaihu DeRabbanan? So what is the reason of the רבנן? Rabbanan? כי
הא דאמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל, Ki ha de'amar Rav Yehuda amar
Shmuel, חכמים תקנו להן לבנות ישראל שיהיו בודקות עצמן שחרית וערבית, Chachamim
tiknu lahen livnos Yisrael sheyihyu bodkos atzman shacharis ve'arvis,
because generally we haven't said it in the משנה, Mishnah, but we're
going to say it, that the general practice is when women, when
the world, the Jewish world was concerned about טומאה וטהרה, tumah vetaharah,
that women would check twice a day to make sure that they
had not become a נדה. niddah. Now the funny thing is that
they would check throughout the month even when they weren't expecting their
period and we'll talk about all of that, but the general practice
was to check twice a day. So first we're going to say
that that was the practice. So חכמים תקנו להן לבנות ישראל שיהיו
בודקות עצמן שחרית וערבית. Chachamim tiknu lahen livnos Yisrael sheyihyu bodkos atzman
shacharis ve'arvis. There was a general practice that the חכמים Chachamim established
to check twice a day. שחרית Shacharis להכשיר של לילה. lehachshir shel
laila. Now when it says שחרית, Shacharis, it doesn't mean like sometime
in the middle of the day, it's clear from context here it
means like first thing in the day. So they would check first
thing in the day in order to make טהור tahor what they
had done the night before, meaning what? Meaning let's say she had
eaten תרומה terumah for the night before, gone into her תרומה terumah
pantry and if she hadn't checked in the morning, she had waited
till the next night to check, right? So then she would have
had to say, oh maybe... and then she found she was טמא
tamei like the next night, she'd have to say she was טמא
tamei when she got to her תרומה terumah the night before. But
if she checks in the morning and sees she's טהור, tahor, then
even if later she finds she's טמא, tamei, at least what she
did the night before is okay. So this is you check and
meaning and assuming it's good, you've now saved what you've done the
night before. You've protected what you've done prior to the check assuming
the check is good. So they checked in the morning in order
to protect what had happened the night before assuming it would be
a good check.
וערבית Ve'arvis and at night, first thing at night, להכשיר של יום,
lehachshir shel yom, in order to protect what had happened during the
day so as if the night check was good, anything that happened
in the day would would also be good.
And then how do you get 24 hours?
One minute. So first let's assume let's accept that all women are
supposed to be checking first thing in the day, first thing at
night. וזו, Vezo, and
this... וזו הואיל ולא בדקה, vezo ho'il velo badka, this woman, since
she didn't check, obviously she didn't check, right? Because the fact that
we have to be concerned about up to 24 hours, if she
had done what she was supposed to be doing, then it would
never go beyond 12 hours because then you would always go to
the last time you checked. So why do we have to put
a limit of 24 hours? Obviously this woman hasn't been doing the
regular checks. So since she did not do the regular checks, הפסידה
עונה. hifsida onah. She's lost a period. Now a period in מסכת
נדה Masechet Niddah means either daytime or nighttime, not 12 hours, but
it means a daytime unit, meaning from sunrise to sunset or from
sunset to sunrise. So imagine this scenario which is she went ahead
and she checked, you know, I don't know, at 5:00 PM and
she found that she had... that she had bled. Now had she
done what she was supposed to have done and checked at sunrise,
then she would have been טמא tamei till... sunrise but no further
and you wouldn't need the 24 hour limit. But she didn't check
till sunrise. Last time she checked was five days ago, okay? So
therefore, what we're going to do is we're going to fine her,
punish her, fine her and say, hey, even if she had done
what she would have done, she would have been טמאה tameiah back
till sunrise. Because she was not doing what she should have been
doing, she's going to have to be טמאה tameiah another unit and
another 12 hours back to the prior sunset. So that makes 24
hours. You see that? So assuming she's now checking when she's supposed
to be checking, which is first thing at night, but she hasn't
checked for the last five days, so if you had been doing
what you would have been doing, you would have been טמאה tameiah
12 hours till the first thing in the morning. Because she hasn't,
again we're not going to go overboard, but there's going to be
a little bit of a consequence for being irresponsible, so we're going
to add another 12 hours and you get to 24. Yes.
This would seem to imply that the תרומה terumah that she would
have handled would have been טמא tamei דרבנן-ly d'rabbanan because it says
as a result of a גזירה. gezeirah.
Yeah, well all of this is, that's true. I mean the whole
fact that we can just cut it off at 24 hours based,
means that we basically פוסקים poskin that מעיקר הדין me'ikar hadin she's
not טמאה tameiah backward. And by the way, it sounds from the
earlier גמרא Gemara and other things make it clear that even הלל
Hillel would agree to that. Everybody agrees in principle like שמאי Shammai
that she's only טמאה tameiah from now, you know, we're not, we
don't have any concern back. All of these concerns about what happened
prior are all דרבנן. d'rabbanan.
Okay. My point was that you know she hadn't checked for five
days and it's like to say to הלל, Hillel, 'Well, you're only
טמא tamei till the last time you checked,' wow, that's what הלל
Hillel says. Okay. So you don't want to fine her too much.
Right? But מעיקר הדין me'ikar hadin she's really not even טמא tamei
12 hours.
Exactly. Okay. So, okay. So that's what he said. מאי עונה? Mai
onah? What do you mean a unit? עונה יתירה, Onah yeteirah, an
extra unit. Meaning obviously the immediate prior unit isn't defined. See anybody,
even if she had done what she was supposed to have been
doing, she would have been טמאה tameiah the previous day, the previous,
like daytime. So it's an extra unit. Not only the previous day
hours, but even the night before that. אמר ליה רב פפא, Amar
leih Rav Papa, says רב פפא Rav Papa לרבא, l'Rava, זימנין דמשכחת
לה ג' עונות במעת לעת, zimnin demashkachat lah gimmel onot b'ma'et l'ma'et,
so sometimes it comes out to three עונות, onot, meaning what? Let's
say she didn't check at 6 PM. Let's say she checked at
3 PM. So you go back 24 hours. That goes into, crosses
over three עונות. onot. Right? Because if you go back 24 hours,
you go back to the prior 3 PM, so you go till
6 AM, that's you're in עונה onah number one. You go back
till the next 6 PM, that's עונה onah number two. And then
from 6 PM you go back till 3 PM, you're into עונה
onah three. So it's only 24 hours but it's three units. You're
crossing into three units. And you framed it that we'll just slap
on an extra unit. So in this case, when it's not at
an end of a unit, it's 24 hours is going to get
us three עונות במעת לעת gimmel onot b'ma'et
l'ma'et like שיעור shi'ur or something?
Yeah. So that's why, and that's why I said that. So, so
the answer
is ג' עונות במעת לעת, gimmel onot b'ma'et l'ma'et, so you have
three עונות onot within 24 hours. The answer is היכא דאמור רבנן
מילתא לא ליפלוג במעת לעת. Heicha d'amur rabbanan milta lo liplug b'ma'et
l'ma'et. The rabbis just, you know, lo plug, they didn't make distinctions.
They said always do 24 hours. Because if the last check is
when it's, if the most recent check is when it's supposed to
be, which is at the end of a unit, then שתי עונות
shtei onot is 24 hours. Right? If it's at 6 PM, then
שתי עונות shtei onot is 24 hours and therefore we're always going
to say 24 hours just to be consistent. Okay.
That's such a great phrase is like lo plug. Yeah. For this
isn't Hebrew we've been saying, I mean these words the rabbis were
speaking Aramaic.
Yeah, it's interesting why it's, why it's exactly switched to Hebrew here.
That's a good point. Maybe, and maybe that is a phrase that
comes from some תנאי-tic Tannai source. You're right.
It goes from Aramaic to Hebrew. It's a very good point. איבעית
אימא, Iba'it eima, if you want you can say, שלא יהא חוטא
נשכר, shelo yehei chotei niskar, that the sinner should not get rewarded.
How is the sinner being rewarded? Because if we would say, well
it's never going to be more than שתי עונות, shtei onot, so
you're only going to go back, you checked at 3 PM, you're
only going to go back like, you know, 20 hours. You're going
to go back till the prior 6 PM, not to the prior
3 PM. So now because you were irresponsible, you don't you know,
you're going to win. It's going to be less than 24 hours.
Now the funny thing is, that's actually not true, because the scenario
we described of 24 hours was when she didn't check at 3
PM but she checked when? At what was I describing? At 6
PM. So actually, she's been irresponsible in the past, yes, but actually
right now, she's being more responsible checking at 3 rather than, so
maybe you look at 3 PM as a late 6 AM rather
than early 6 PM. But it's funny that it calls it חוטא
נשכר chotei niskar because if anything, right, the classic case was when
she waited till 6 PM then we say okay that we understand
two. But here, we don't want you to be נשכר niskar because
you you know, were a חוטא. chotei. You weren't a חוטא, chotei,
but maybe you're חוטא chotei in general here. So we don't want
some of these scenarios to get you to be less than 24
hours.
You're still being irresponsible. In the sense that she didn't check first
thing in the morning.
I understand, that's what I'm saying. But so is the woman who
did 6:00 PM, but right. So in general in her practice she's
been חוטא, chote, so we don't want some of these things, but
look at the answer at the end of the גמרא. Gemara.
Even the 3:00 PM one is considered deficient because it's late.
That's what I'm saying. You look at the 3:00 PM as a
late 6:00 AM, not as an early 6:00 PM. Right. Okay, so
the גמרא Gemara says, so let's see what the גמרא's Gemara answer
is: מאי בינייהו, mai beinaihu, איכא בינייהו דאשתנסה ולא בדקה. ika beinaihu
de'ishtenesa velo badka. Would there be a difference between these two approaches?
Yes. The difference would be if it wasn't אונס. ones. If she
wasn't being irresponsible, she was trying to check let's say at 6:00
AM and something happened, there was an emergency, she couldn't. So in
that case, you wouldn't call her a חוטא chote and you wouldn't
have a problem of saying only go back one, you know, till
the prior עונה, ona, but not a full 24 hours. So anyway,
obviously although the גמרא Gemara puts that out as a theoretical possibility,
it seems clear at the end it's a type of לא פלוג,
lo plug, 24 hours, and the end of the גמרא Gemara recognizes
it's a compromise position, but it's explaining that the answer is based
here more on like sort of like policy concerns than on biological
realities. The real concern about how טמא tamei she is does not
go backwards. But in terms of how we are going to approach
it, we don't want to be overly strict, but it has to
be something, there has to be some consequence for being irresponsible, so
it's going to be 24 hours.
Right, you can say that for instance you know she had, she
was with her husband, that he has to bring a קרבן korban
for בעל נדה baal nidda and so forth. Right, right, no, no,
absolutely.
This is all דרבנן. derabbanan. And we're going to see more of
that as we move through. Correct, we're going to see more of
that as we move through. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara goes
on. וכל אשה שיש לה וסת. vechol isha sheyesh la veset. Now
this was the next line of the משנה Mishnah said anyone that
has a regular period, so then everybody would agree, even הלל, Hillel,
that she's only טמאה temea from the moment she sees. Now what
does that mean? It means what we're actually going to discuss in
a minute, but for simplicity's sake, it means when she bleeds during
the period of time she's expecting her period, then she doesn't have
to be concerned, I mean she finds then that she has bled,
she doesn't have to be concerned that it happened earlier. We can
assume if she's bled now and this was when she was expecting
her period, that this is when she bled, and it was not
in a prior time, because of the fact that this is her
expected time is what is significant is indicative. What? No, no, no,
that's going to be a later discussion. We're not going to get
into the details of that just yet, but let's take a look.
So the גמרא Gemara says like
this: לימא מתניתין רבי דוסא היא ולא רבנן. leima matnitin Rabbi Dosa
hi velo Rabbanan. Let's say our משנה Mishnah is רבי דוסא Rabbi
Dosa and not the Rabbis. What רבי דוסא? Rabbi Dosa? דתניא, detanya,
it was taught in a ברייתא. braita. רבי אליעזר אומר Rabbi Eliezer
omer ארבע נשים דיין שעתן. arba nashim dayan sha'atan. Four women, whenever
they find blood, they can assume it just happened right now besides
the woman who has a וסת. veset. Four women, you always assume
it happened just now because these are women that would have had
a right not to be expecting blood at all. Who are these
four women? בתולה, betula, literally means a virgin, but the גמרא Gemara
says it doesn't mean a virgin, it means בתולת דמים, betulat damim,
a woman that has never had her period. Okay, so a young
girl who's never had her period, whenever she bleeds you assume it
just, this is the first time and it just happened now and
it did not happen prior.
מעוברת me'uberet a pregnant woman, מניקה menika nursing women, וזקנה vezekena and
an elderly woman, post-menopausal. So all of these women are women that
should not be having their period anyway, and therefore if they bled,
it is, you assume it only happened now. So that's, so that's
a nice addition to our משנה, Mishnah, we'll get to that later.
Would a זקנה zekena be considered נדה nidda and not a זבה?
zava?
What? Yes, because נדה nidda and זבה zava is not about the
reality of menstruation, it's about more formal rules, we'll worry about that
later. רבי דוסא אומר כל אשה שיש לה וסת דיה שעתה. Rabbi
Dosa omer kol isha sheyesh la veset daya sha'ata. Any woman who,
so this seems like he's not arguing on רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer,
maybe adding or whatever, any woman that has a וסת veset when
she finds, that's what דיה שעתה daya sha'ata her hour is sufficient.
When she finds, it's when we assume it happened, not prior, because
she actually found blood at the time she was expecting her period.
Now, there you don't really see a debate if it is a
debate of רבי דוסא Rabbi Dosa and the Rabbis, but the גמרא
Gemara assumes that if there's a רבי דוסא Rabbi Dosa saying it,
presumably there's some generic חכמים Chachamim out there that disagrees with רבי
דוסא. Rabbi Dosa. It's only רבי דוסא Rabbi Dosa that says דיה
שעתה, daya sha'ata, presumably there's a majority voice doesn't agree with that.
And our משנה Mishnah said the same thing רבי דוסא Rabbi Dosa
said, that if a woman bleeds during the time she's expecting her
period, דיה שעתה. daya sha'ata. So the גמרא Gemara says, maybe our
משנה Mishnah is only רבי דוסא? Rabbi Dosa? So it says no.
אפילו תימא רבנן. afilu teima Rabbanan. Maybe even the generic, you know,
Rabbis that disagree with רבי דוסא. Rabbi Dosa. Maybe there's two ways
that they can be debating. עד כאן לא פליגי רבנן עליה דרבי
דוסא. ad kan lo paligi Rabbanan alei deRabbi Dosa. Maybe the debate
of the Rabbis and רבי דוסא Rabbi Dosa אלא שלא בשעת וסתה.
ela shelo bish'at vestah. Here's another, I've been giving you the scenario
that this woman bled during when she's expecting her period and therefore
you assume it happened just now, but if you actually think about
it, that's not the most analogous case to the pregnant and the
nursing woman. The pregnant and the nursing woman is a woman who
has a right not to be expecting her period. So what's the
analogy to that? The woman with a regular period at the rest
of the month. So maybe that's what רבי דוסא Rabbi Dosa is
talking about, and that's why it's a דעת יחיד. da'at yachid. Can
a woman who has a regular period the rest of the month
assume that she had, that it was not going to happen and
if it happened it only happened right now? Okay, so the having
a period is a strong enough predictor to Also predict or to
be a proof that, a prima facie proof that she is not
bleeding during the rest of the month and therefore if she finds
blood it only happened just now. Yes.
So setting this off against the four these four categories, none of
these have a וסת. Vesset. Right. So how can we say?
The four categories are category of מסולקת דמים, Mesulekes Damim, what the
גמרא Gemara calls מסולקת דמים. Mesulekes Damim. So maybe רבי דוסא Rebbi
Dosa is saying a woman with a וסת Vesset during the rest
of the month is מסולקת דמים. Mesulekes Damim. Conceptually that works very
well. He's saying she's מסולקת דמים. Mesulekes Damim. A woman who doesn't
have a period, how does she know when she's going to bleed?
But a woman who has a period is מסולקת דמים Mesulekes Damim
during the rest of the month, that makes a lot of sense.
So maybe that's his position and that's where there's a debate. אבל
בשעת וסת, Aval bishas Vesset, if she bleeds when she was expecting
her period, מודה ליה, modei lei, maybe everybody would agree that she
can assume she bled just now. The only question is how strong
is the period to say that the rest of the month is
מסולקת דמים. Mesulekes Damim. But to say when she bled during her
period that it happened just now, maybe everybody would agree.
You could almost say the other way around. If she's expecting her
period, maybe it happened yesterday.
No, but it's only expecting, assume, שעת וסת shas Vesset means you
have a very regular period. So this woman is so regular she
always bleeds twenty eighth day on the dot. And now she saw
blood on the twenty eighth day. So why she should be concerned
it happened on the twenty seventh? It was predicted on the twenty
eighth and she found it on the twenty eighth, she should assume
it happened on the twenty eighth. Right, so that case everybody could
agree to. Yes?
I mean the evidence, a single day we're talking about?
A single day, correct. A week? Correct. Yeah, a single day, not
even, it's even more precise within an עונה, Onah, like daytime or
nighttime and so on. So when the actual evidence confirms the prediction
then we're going to assume that's exactly what happened. We're not going
to be concerned about למפרע. l'mafrea. But if it happens at an
earlier time, that's questionable if you can say that she's מסולקת דמים
Mesulekes Damim at an earlier time.
But if she bleeds five p.m. and on the twenty eighth day
when she always bleeds on the twenty eighth day, but do we
say why don't we just say that it could be maybe ten
a.m.? That, it could be.
If her וסת Vesset is that broad to include the entire period
then obviously she'd have to be concerned the entire period.
Let's keep on going. The גמרא Gemara says ומתניתין בשעת וסת ודברי
הכל. u-matnisin bishas Vesset vedivrei hakol. Our משנה Mishnah is talking about
that she saw on when she was expecting her period and everybody
could agree there that דיה שעתה. dayah sha'atah. So now the גמרא
Gemara says fine, מכלל דרבי דוסא אפילו שלא בשעת וסת אמר. miklal
d'Rebbi Dosa afilu shelo bishas Vesset amar. So you're telling me now
that רבי דוסא Rebbi Dosa would say that she's considered מסולקת דמים
Mesulekes Damim when it's not during her period and that it's דיה
שעתה. dayah sha'atah. So מאן תנא להא דתנו רבנן? man tanna le-ha
de-sanu rabbanan? So now if that's true let's take a look at
this next ברייתא Braisa and figure out who is the author of
it. אשה שיש לה וסת, Ishah sheyesh lah Vesset, a woman who
has a regular period, כתמה טמאה למפרע. kisma tameiah l'mafrea. Her stains,
not her ראייה, re'iyah, not like she actually sees that she's bleeding,
but she finds her garment has some bloodstains on it. Now this
idea of a garment has a bloodstain, we said it was a
pretty unhygienic society so A you had to be concerned it came
from elsewhere but B even if it didn't come from
elsewhere, who knows when the stain got on the garment? I mean
if she sees she's bleeding she knows now she just bled and
the question is how much earlier did it start? But if it's
a stain on the garment maybe it got there a week ago,
a day ago, who knows? So what's the הלכה halachah about stains
on garments and how retroactively do we have to be concerned that
it occurred? So כתמה טמאה למפרע, kisma tameiah l'mafrea, it says she
does have to be concerned retroactively. Now the retroactively by garments is
not twenty four hours back, it's till the last time she cleaned
the garment which could be a while, I don't know how often
they did
laundry. כתמה טמאה למפרע. kisma tameiah l'mafrea. Now why is it appropriate
to be מטמא metamei the garments retroactively?
שאם תראה שלא בשעת וסת מטמאה מעת לעת, she-im tireh she-lo bishas
Vesset metameiah me'es le'es, because it's not we're not being more strict
by the stains than we are by a normal ראייה re'iyah because
even if she had a normal ראייה re'iyah as long as it
wasn't during her time of her period she would have had to
worry twenty four hours back. So the same way for this woman
we will sometimes tell her worry twenty four hours back by a
real ראייה, re'iyah, we're also entitled to say that if it's a
stain you have to worry back to the last time you laundered
your clothes. What we're basically trying to say is it's not going
to be
completely paradoxical or ironic that we're going to be strict by stains
and not strict by an actual ראייה. re'iyah. Because even by a
ראייה re'iyah there'll be times we'll be strict backwards if it was
שלא בשעת
וסת. shelo bishas Vesset. I know, so there still are differences but
it's not like completely absurd. That's the basic point of this. But
for us what's important is that it says for a woman who
sees שלא בשעת וסת shelo bishas Vesset she's concerned twenty four hours
back. So now we've said that רבי דוסא Rebbi Dosa would disagree.
He would have called her מסולקת דמים Mesulekes Damim during that period.
So the גמרא Gemara says נימא רבנן היא ולא רבי דוסא. neima
rabbanan hi v'lo Rebbi Dosa. That sounds like it's the rabbis and
not רבי דוסא Rebbi Dosa because you just said רבי דוסא Rebbi
Dosa would say that not during her period time she's דיה שעתה.
dayah sha'atah. So now the גמרא Gemara backpedals. It says okay maybe
everybody does agree that. אפילו תימא רבי דוסא. Afilu teima Rebbi Dosa.
Maybe you're right, maybe everybody agrees that not during her period time
it is twenty four hours, it's not דיה שעתה. dayah sha'atah. עד
כאן לא. Ad kan lo.
Maybe you're right. Maybe they're only debating when she saw during the
period whether she's דיה שעתה. daya shata. אבל שלא בשעת וסתה Aval
shelo besha'as vestah when it's not during the period מודו לו, modo
lo, then everybody agrees you do go 24 hours back. So now
we have taken back what we said, rather than saying, which is
actually now we are the more strict opinion. Before we said actually
everybody agrees when it's בשעת וסתה, besha'as vestah, דיה שעתה, daya shata,
the debate is שלא בשעת וסתה, shelo besha'as vestah, is that דיה
שעתה, daya shata, is she מטמא מעת לעת. metamma me'eis le'eis. Now
we're saying, no no, maybe you're right. Maybe you're right what you
suggested first. Our משנה, mishnah, maybe that is debated and it's only
רבי דוסא, Rabbi Dosa, and the debate is בשעת וסתה, besha'as vestah,
if it's דיה שעתה daya shata when she bleeds when she was
expected. But when she bleeds during the rest of the month, maybe
there everybody agrees that it is a 24-hour wait, okay, which is
a more—a stricter way of reading the debate. ומתניתין בשעת וסתה ורבי
דוסא היא, U-masnisin besha'as vestah ve-Rabbi Dosa hi, our משנה, mishnah, yes,
is not unanimous, our משנה mishnah is only if she bled during
the time of—during the period, and it is
רבי דוסא.
Rabbi Dosa. וברייתא דברי הכל, Ve-baraisa divrei ha-kol, and the ברייתא, braisa,
because of three opinions, בית הלל,
Beis Hillel, בית שמאי Beis Shammai and the חכמים. Chachamim. Okay, no—actually,
yeah, I mean and then it becomes the סתם של משנה stam
shel mishnah anyway. וברייתא דברי הכל, Ve-baraisa divrei ha-kol, and the ברייתא
braisa that says that a woman who bleeds שלא בשעת וסתה shelo
besha'as vestah has to be concerned 24 hours back, that everybody would
agree. So do you understand that רבי דוסא ורבנן Rabbi Dosa ve-rabbanan
would agree about whether a woman has to be concerned backwards if
she has a וסת. veses. Okay, so which—which scenario we're talking about,
bleeding during the וסת veses or שלא בשעת וסתה? shelo besha'as vestah?
So the first approach we did was a more lenient read, that
if it's בשעת וסתה besha'as vestah
that everybody agrees you don't have to be concerned, and if it's
שלא בשעת וסתה shelo besha'as vestah that's a debate, not during the
expected time is she מטמא מעת לעת. metamma me'eis le'eis. Now we're
taking the stricter approach. שלא בשעת וסתה Shelo besha'as vestah
is everybody agrees you have to be concerned backwards, and the only
question is בשעת וסתה. besha'as vestah. רבי דוסא Rabbi Dosa says דיה
שעתה, daya shata, חכמים Chachamim say no, and
our משנה mishnah is רבי דוסא. Rabbi Dosa. Well what—and then what's—what's
up with that? That is דברי הכל, divrei ha-kol, everybody assumes that
שלא בשעת וסתה shelo besha'as vestah you are concerned 24 hours back.
Well no, but wait, what—I thought you said the last time—no no,
but that—we'll get to stains later, but that ברייתא braisa was comparing
stains to ראייה. re'iyah. That since by ראייה re'iyah you're concerned 24
hours back, we can also make you concerned retroactively for stains.
Right, but you said till the last examination.
Oh yeah, so—okay fine. We'll get to that more in a bit.
So the גמרא Gemara says ולוקמה איפכא, Ve-loukmah ipcha, why not go
back to what you're trying—tried to say before, the משנה mishnah is
דברי הכל divrei ha-kol and the whole debate is שלא בשעת וסתה?
shelo besha'as vestah? No. כיון דאיכא לאוקמה לקולא ולחומרא, לחומרא מוקמינן. Keivan
de-ika le-oukmah le-kulla u-le-chumra, le-chumra mokminan.
So some people sort of feel that this is the—that this is
the approach of too many—of too many פוסקים posekim or too many
Jews, which is, since you can go leniently and strict, why not
go strict?
So which basically means that—you know, תוספות Tosafos even says, well what's
the הוה אמינא, hava amina, of course we would have said that,
you know, which is sometimes funny because sometimes the גמרא Gemara actually
אדרבה adaraba emphasizes the
importance of כוח דהיתרא עדיף. koach de-heisera adif. But here what it's
saying is, and there's interesting questions, this is
more—more something about not how we assume a debate takes place, but
more a principle we know about like
certain—הקש. hekkesh. If you would link a פסוק pasuk one way and
link it another way, so לחומרא מקשינן, לקולא לא מקשינן. le-chumra makshinan,
le-kulla lo makshinan. So the question is, is this just like a
rule, you know, if you can go either way you—you interpret it
in the more strict way, or is it more like a playing
it safe type of approach? Since we don't know where they debated,
we should play it safe and assume the version of the debate
which is a stricter version rather than a more lenient version. Anyway,
the גמרא Gemara obviously does not do this all the time, but
it is interesting to hear that articulated. Yes.
But normally ספק דרבנן לקולא. Safek de-rabbanan le-kulla.
Exactly, ספק דרבנן לקולא.
safek
de-rabbanan le-kulla.
This is all rabbinic and right, so you're absolutely correct, which is
what makes this, you know, the interesting thing is, I—I would have
to check how many times the גמרא Gemara says this, and clearly
even though it doesn't explicitly say the opposite, many times it implicitly
is operating, you know, with a different understanding. And I think that
this is more derived from a similar principle that you have by
the י"ג מידות Yud-Gimmel Middos and by—when you're—you can מקיש makkish a
פסוק, pasuk, when you can connect the פסוק pasuk to another one,
and there's interesting תוספות Tosafos there that discuss like also how global
and absolute that principle is. So.
Also what I was going to say is that, you know, this
reminds me of the יצחק דב, Yitzchak Dov, who had said—no, בית
שמאי ובית הלל, Beis Shammai ve-Beis Hillel, right? You know,
when we deal with these טהרות taharos issues, people get all hung
up about it. So that—maybe that we're seeing it in this particular
context. That's an interesting point.
Right, since the whole thing is a world—here's all of these extreme
חומרות, chumros, so we should assume anyway people are being more מחמיר.
machmir. Could be. I would have to check where else, how—you know,
the other contexts of where that phrase is used. Okay, so now
the גמרא Gemara goes on. קתני שבכתם שלא בשעת וסתה מטמא מעת
לעת. Kasani she-bekesem shelo besha'as vestah metamma me'eis le'eis.
So we said that if a woman does bleed not during her
period, then we are concerned it happened earlier and it's 24 hours
back. And now we're saying that רבי דוסא וחכמים Rabbi Dosa ve-chachamim
would both agree with that. She's not דיה שעתה. daya shata. טעמא
דאישה שיש לה וסת הוא דפליגי רבנן ואין כתמה לראייתה. Ta'ama de-ishah
she-yesh lah veses hu de-paligi rabbanan ve-ein kesemah le-re'iyasah. So what we
are saying now is that with a woman that has a וסת,
veses, that's when we are, you know, we're distinguishing between her כתם
kesem and her ראייה. re'iyah. Which means what? Which means, hold on
just one second. Right, so it's phrased in a funny way, because
it's really not about distinguishing, but it means like this: since for
this woman of יש לה וסת, yesh lah veset, since there are
times where she's חושש choshesh retroactively, when she bleeds שלא בשעת וסתה,
shelo b'sha'at vestah, we're entitled to say that when she sees a
stain, we're going to be חושש choshesh retroactively even though that is
different than what she would normally be true by her. What would
normally be true by a woman with a regular period? That she
would bleed during her period and she wouldn't be חושש choshesh retroactively.
But nevertheless we're entitled to make her stain טמא tamei retroactively because
there are times when even she will be טמא tamei retroactively, right?
Is that clear? At any point? Yeah, at any point. Okay, but
the point is so with this woman we're entitled to make her
stains different than her status, because even sometimes with her it's true
that it's טמא tamei retroactively. That's what the גמרא Gemara means. So
with this woman we're entitled to do that. So what's כתמים וראיה?
ketamim v're'iyah? We're distinguishing between her stains and when she actually sees.
Why are we entitled to say stains retroactively and sees not? Because
sometimes even when she sees it's retroactively. Right, so therefore we're entitled
to distinguish. Sometimes you're right. Exactly. השאר נשים, hash'ar nashim, but other
women שאמרו חכמים דיין שעתן, she'amru chachamim dayan sha'atan, where the rabbis
said that they only worry when they see and they don't have
any times they worry retroactively. Who are the women that never worry
retroactively? All those women we said before, right? The post-menopause and the
pregnant and the nursing, they'll never have a time, no matter when
they see, that they're worry retroactively because they're always מסולקת דמים. mesuleket
damim. So for those women, כתמן כראייתן, kitman k're'iyatan, the implication is
that if they see a stain, they don't have to worry retroactively
about the stain.
So the basic point the גמרא Gemara is saying is it was
implicit from the previous ברייתא braita that we would only say your
stains are
טמא tamei retroactively if sometimes it's true when you actually
bleed. But if it's never true when you bleed that it's retroactively,
we won't say it by your stains as well. Okay, that makes
sense. מני? Mani? Who's that going like? רבי חנינא בן אנטיגנוס היא.
Rabbi Chanina ben Antignos hi. That's רבי חנינא בן אנטיגנוס Rabbi Chanina
ben Antignos who
says that point explicitly. דאמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל משום רבי חנינא
בן אנטיגנוס, D'amar Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel mishum Rabbi Chanina ben Antignos,
because we said in the name of רבי חנינא בן אנטיגנוס: Rabbi
Chanina ben Antignos: כל הנשים כתמן טמא למפרע, kol hanashim kitman tamei
l'mafrei'a, all women their stains are טמא tamei retroactively. ובנשים שאמרו חכמים
דיין שעתן, u'v'nashim she'amru chachamim dayan sha'atan, but regarding the women that
the rabbis said that when they see it's enough, meaning those four
women, כתמן כראייתן. kitman k're'iyatan. What? Except for those, right. Okay, כתמן
כראייתן, kitman k're'iyatan, their stains are just like when they see and
they are not טמא tamei retroactively. חוץ, Chutz, there's one exception, but
it's an exception לקולא. l'kula. מתינוקת שלא הגיע זמנה לראות, mitinoket shelo
higia zmanah lir'ot, a young child who has not only she has
not yet had her period, it's not even yet the time for
her period, right? She is still prepubescent. So that type of a
child, שאפילו, she'afilu, not only would we say we're not מטמא metamei
retroactively, we're going to be even more lenient. שאפילו סדין שלה מלוכלכין
בדם, she'afilu sadin shela meluchlachim b'dam, even if her bedsheets are filled
with blood, are stained with blood, אין חוששין לה היא טהורה. ein
chosheshin la hi tehorah. We're not even going to be concerned that
she's bled. Okay, because it's not like she's twelve and she hasn't
had her period yet, then we would say now she's had her
period. But this is a girl who's six, okay? So therefore and
again it's an unhygienic society, so it's not unreasonable to assume that
even though she has no idea where the blood came from, who
knows, maybe there were bedbugs, who knows what it was, and therefore
she'll be totally טהורה. tehorah. So that's an exception לקולא. l'kula. But
the basic point is is that the women who are מסולקות דמים,
mesulekot damim, since they are never טמא tamei retroactively when they see,
so too even their stains. Of course you would say, lots of
you'd say, of course it's a קל וחומר, kal v'chomer, but as
we've been implying it's not, because a woman could be טמא tamei
twenty-four hours back, but the stain could be till the last time
the garment was washed, because the stain like it could be from
there from a long time and you wouldn't have seen it. So
it's not unreasonable although the חכמים Chachamim are more lenient in general,
it's a purely rabbinic category, it's not unreasonable to be concerned even
more, you know, backwards, but these women are not—do not have to
be. Is the woman טמא tamei till last time she's laundered or
the garment is טמא tamei till last time? Well, the garment is
טמא tamei and she was in contact with the garment and she's
טמא tamei but not טמא tamei well yes, you know, no, I'm
sorry, I misspoke. She is—she is טמא tamei as well, yes, because
if the garment is טמא, tamei, I mean I was thinking another
woman, another woman would obviously only she came in contact with the
garment. But since we're saying that she's טמא tamei because it came
from her, then yes, she also becomes a נדה niddah as a
result of us being מטמא metamei the כתמים. ketamim. And she is
טמא tamei retroactively till the last time the garment got laundered, yes.
Okay, wait, so it's only twenty-four hours when it's שלא בשעת וסתה
shelo b'sha'at vestah and then she sees a stain? It's twenty-four hours,
well according to our משנה Mishnah that says שעת וסתה sha'at vestah
is different, it's twenty-four hours for any woman who doesn't have a
regular וסת, veset, or with a woman who has a regular וסת
veset who sees שלא בשעת וסתה. shelo b'sha'at vestah. Then it's twenty-four
hours. Yeah. But it's a week if—so when is it a week?
Several—well it's the last time she laundered. If it—if it's not— So
maybe it does, although the משנה Mishna discusses she stood up and
she found it on the bed. Right. So let's assume that a,
let's assume that a stain means for now, but it's I'm telling
you at the outset that it's a little imprecise. But for now
we're going to assume that a stain means that it's on some
garment that might not have come from her, we don't know it
definitely came from her, and a ראייה Re'iyah means that it definitely
came from her. She was sitting on the bed, it was clean
before she got up and now there's blood, she finds it on
her tight-fitting underwear on the inside of the underwear, okay, that would
be a real ראייה, Re'iyah, not a כתם. Kesem. All right. For
now we'll assume that definition. Let's keep on going. Okay. ומי אית
ליה לרבי חנינא? Umi Isalei L'Rabbi Chanina? So now we see that
according to that, if a woman is never חושש choshesh retroactively, she's
מסולקת דמים, mesulekes damim, the same is true about the כתמים. kesamim.
ומי אית ליה לרבי חנינא כתם כלל? Umi Isalei L'Rabbi Chanina kesem
klal? One minute, since when does רבי חנינא Rabbi Chanina hold of
כתמים kesamim at all? At least for these women. דתניא, Dasanya, we
turn the ברייתא: Braisa: כל הנשים כתמן טמא, Kol hanashim kesman tamei,
all women, their stains are טמא, tamei, if they find their stains
again like on a garment and not sure where it came from
and they can't attribute it elsewhere. ונשים שאמרו חכמים דיין שעתן, Vinashim
she'omru chachamim dayan sha'atan, but the women that the rabbis said that
their time is enough, meaning those that are מסולקות דמים, mesulekos damim,
כתמן טמא. kesman tamei. Also their כתם kesem is טמא. tamei. Maybe
not retroactively, but at least it's טמא. tamei. רבי חנינא בן אנטיגנוס
אומר: Rabbi Chanina Ben Antigonus omer: נשים שאמרו חכמים דיין שעתן אין
להם כתם. Nashim she'omru chachamim dayan sha'atan ein lahem kesem. No! If
these women are not expecting, you know, are מסולקות דמים, mesulekos damim,
right? They're pregnant or they're, you know, postmenopausal, pre-menopausal, all these women,
then we'll assume the stain came from elsewhere. We're not going to
say it's טמא tamei at all. Not just we're not going to
assume it happened now, we're not going to assume it came from
them. Period. Their כתם kesem is not טמא. tamei. Okay, so that's
a pretty strong statement. Of course, it doesn't fit with the previous
statement what he said that only by the תינוקת, tinokes, right? Only
by the underage girl. Here he's saying it's true by all these
women. So the גמרא Gemara is going to modify his name. What?
I just said the name of him. Oh, that's a good point.
So let's see what the גמרא Gemara says. מאי לאו אין להם
כתם כלל? Mai lav ein lahem kesem klal? Does that mean that
there's no כתם kesem at all? לא, Lo, אין להם כתם למפרע.
ein lahem kesem l'afreya. No. He doesn't mean, he doesn't mean it's
not a כתם kesem and טמא tamei at all. He means it's
not a טמא, tamei, it's not a full status of a כתם
kesem to worry retroactively. אבל יש להם כתם מכאן ולהבא. Aval yeish
lahem kesem mikan ul'aba. It would, at least certainly he would agree
that it would be טמא tamei from here on in. It just
means that we're not concerned retroactively by this category class of women.
מכלל Miklal says the גמרא Gemara דתנא קמא סבר אפילו למפרע? d'Tanna
Kamma savar afilu l'afreya? אפילו למפרע? Afilu l'afreya? So you mean to
tell me the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma says even retroactively? Meaning now,
now the גמרא Gemara is saying is, you know, this position that
we've said oh this is רבי חנינא בן אנטיגנוס, Rabbi Chanina Ben
Antigonus, it's very persuasive that these women that are מסולקות דמים, mesulekos
damim, that you know if you have a stain and you don't
even know where the stain came from, at least not to be
מטמא mitamei her retroactively to assume it happened earlier. So are you
telling me that there's a position that is strict about that? אין,
In, yes, רבי מאיר היא. Rabbi Meir hi. דמחמיר גבי כתמים. Dimachmir
gabei kesamim. Yes, it's רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, and we find in
general רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir is strict by כתמים. kesamim. תוספות Tosafos
quotes other places רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir is strict by כתמים. kesamim.
And here as well. דתניא, Dasanya, we turn the ברייתא: Braisa: כל
הנשים כתמן טמא למפרע. Kol hanashim kesman tamei l'afreya. All women, if
they find the stain, it's טמא tamei retroactively. I might have said
24 hours before, but I misspoke. Again, by the stains, to the
last time the garment was laundered. ונשים שאמרו חכמים דיין שעתן, Vinashim
she'omru chachamim dayan sha'atan, how about the women that we say their
time is enough, meaning when they actually see that they don't have
to be concerned backward, the women who are מסולקות דמים, mesulekos damim,
כתמן טמא למפרע דברי רבי מאיר. kesman tamei l'afreya divrei Rabbi Meir.
Same הלכה. halacha. Their כתם kesem is still, is still טמא tamei
going back to the last time it was laundered. Here, now רבי
חנינא בן אנטיגנוס אומר: Rabbi Chanina Ben Antigonus omer: לא, No, ונשים
שאמרו חכמים דיין שעתן כתמן כראייתן. Nashim she'omru chachamim dayan sha'atan kesman
kir'iyasan. Their stain is just like when they see, which makes it
again clear that he's not saying it's טהור. tahor. Yes, when they
have a stain they're טמא, tamei, but not retroactively. The same way
when they see they're not concerned retroactively, when they have a stain
it's also not retroactively. ושלא הגיע זמנה לראות, Veshelo higia zmanah liros,
however, did I skip a line? ותינוקת שהגיע זמנה לראות יש לה
כתם, Vetinokes shehigia zmanah liros yeish lah kesem, a young girl who
has reached her time to see, you know, who has not yet
had her period but it's, but she could be, she's already, you
know, reached puberty, then she has a כתם kesem but not retroactively
because she has not yet had her period. ושלא הגיע זמנה לראות,
Veshelo higia zmanah liros, if she has not yet her time, then
אין לה כתם. ein lah kesem. Then even if there's stains on
the bed, we assume it's not from her. ואימתי הגיע זמנה לראות?
V'eimaisai higia zmanah liros? When is it considered to be that her
period is expected, you know, is expected and then she bleeds it's
a כתם kesem and that she finds the stain it's טמא? tamei?
משהגיעו ימי הנעורים. Mishehigiu yemei hani'urim. When the time of youth comes.
What does that mean? So רש"י Rashi says it means either physical
signs of puberty like pubic hair or 12 years old or an
age that we say is assumed to be the time. Whichever comes
first. Okay. So what have we seen until now? We have introduced,
well we've still discussed more the idea of concerned retroactively, where they
get the 24 hours from, from a certain type of a קנס.
knas. What we've also seen now is this category of women that
are not concerned retroactively, מסולקות דמים, mesulekos damim, women that either postmenopausal,
pre-menopausal, you know, pregnant and so on, that those women that... not
during the period is she considered מסולקת דמים. mesulekes damim. And the
final issue that we've seen until this point is the issue of
כתם, ketem, when it's a stain on a garment. Okay? And there
when it's a stain on the garment, on the one hand, that
whole category is rabbinic and on the one hand there are times
when we could maybe even be very lenient, like this girl שלא
הגיע זמנה לראות, shelo higia zmana liros, so she's not even טמא.
tamei. But on the other hand, there's actually a possibility of being
stricter because there you really don't know when it got on the
garment, and nevertheless the general principle is here is that for the
women who are מסולקות דמים, mesulekos damim, they don't have to be
concerned retroactively when the stain is on the garment, they only have
to be concerned when they find it. However, for a woman who
is normally concerned retroactively when she bleeds, then for the כתם, ketem,
you don't just go back 24 hours, you go to the last
time the garment is laundered, and there you are seeing where stains
can sometimes be more strict. And this again, this כתם, ketem, this
garment is not like you said her tight-fitting underwear. Right, right, correct.
Like my friend who told us about the שושנת העמקים. Shoshanat HaAmakim.
Yeah, for now we're assuming כתם ketem means that at least there
was the possibility that it came from elsewhere as opposed to ראייה,
re'iyah, which is she's sitting on a bed, she got up, there
was a lot. Okay. Yes. רב הונא Rav Huna disagrees with that
for all women it's retroactive. Yeah, yeah, exactly. All right, so now
we get to the next point in the משנה mishna about המשמשת
בעדים, hamishameshes b'edim, and this certainly changes the discussion a little bit.
It says that a woman who is having sex and before she,
or a woman who when she, prior, when she has sex, uses
עדים, edim, literally witnesses. An עד eid is called what we would
call a בדיקה bedikah cloth. It's a witness because it bears testimony
to whether she's been bleeding or not. So if a woman has
been checking for blood before and after she's had sex, then she
doesn't want to have sex when she's a נדה, niddah, she wouldn't
want to know that she was a נדה niddah while she was
having sex, whatever the case was. Then that check also helps for
טהרה. taharah. So if she checked before she had sex at 11:00
at night and she checked and she was טהורה tehorah and then
she checked again at 6:00 in the morning and she found that
she was טמאה, temeah, so she doesn't have to be חושש chosesh
prior to 11:00 at night. That check is good enough to tell
you don't have to be concerned. You know, that retroactive concern stops.
Not only does it stop at the regular morning and evening check,
which we said before was the standard, it even stops at these
checks, which is pretty significant. Did she check before or after? Well,
we're going to talk about it. Let's read the גמרא. gemara. המשמשת
בעדים. hamishameshes b'edim. So says the גמרא, gemara, אמר רב יהודה אמר
שמואל עד שלפני תשמיש אינו כפתיחה. amar Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel, eid
she'lifnei tashmish eino k'fitichah. The עד eid used before תשמיש tashmish does
not limit the 24 hours, period. Okay, or whatever the period is
until the last time you checked. You can't use the check from
right before sex. מאי טעמא? mai ta'ama? What's the reason? אמר רב
קטינא, amar Rav Kattina, מתוך שמהומה לביתה. mitoch she'mehuma l'beisa. Because she
is literally hurried to her home, there's got to be a better
word, but anyway, hurried for her home, therefore she doesn't check well.
So it means because she's, you know, eager to have sex, she's
getting ready to have sex, so she's not taking the patience and
the time that she needs. But I want to make a point
of בייתה beisah because we're actually going to see it, we're going
to come up to it in a minute about the metaphor used.
I mean, חז"ל chazal in general use euphemisms like sex is תשמיש
המיטה, tashmish hamitah, using the bed. Okay, but at least that's more
literal than בית bayis here. What's the idea of בית? bayis? בית,
bayis, well right, so it could be, meaning בית bayis sometimes is
referred to in, you know, is a word that refers to actually
a man's wife, very often in the גמרא gemara is referred to
his ביתו, beiso, right, and the Aramaic word for wife is דביתיה,
devaseih, the house of. Okay, ביתו זו אשתו beiso zu ishto and
so on. Of course here it's a little funny, it says her
בית. bayis. So, but also as we are going to see, the
חכמים chachamim used the whole metaphor of a home for the anatomy
of a woman, the inner anatomy, משלו משל חכמים באשה בית ועליה
וחדר ופרוזדור mashlu mashal chachamim b'ishah bayis v'aliyah v'cheder v'prosdor and so
on. So that the interior of the woman, the uterus and the
vagina and all of this are the various like parts of a
structure of a house. Okay, and the whole idea that, you know,
this בית, bayis, you know, the whole sense of בית bayis is
that there's an interior. So number one, a woman's checking is interior,
but you know that whole sort of emphasis on association of woman
and home and interiority and so on. So that seems to be
the context here, מהומה לביתה, mehuma l'beisa, but the point is that
she knows she's about
to be having sex and therefore she's not
patient as she needs to be to do a good job. So
the גמרא gemara spells that out. וכי מהומה לביתה מאי הוי? v'chi
mehuma l'beisa mai havi? So what? If she's eager to have sex,
you know, how does that affect whether it's a good בדיקה bedikah
or not? So the גמרא gemara says, מתוך שמהומה לביתה, mitoch she'mehuma
l'beisa, no, because she is so, you know, eager, there's got to
be a better word, let's say, what, eager, yeah, I guess. Anyway,
but sort of, anyway, אינה מכנסת לחורין. eina machneses l'chorin. She does
not enter into the nooks. bring the cloth into literally the nooks
and the crannies. So this is a real consistent use
of this house metaphor because I think it's clearly taken from, you
know,
when a woman does a check it's called a בדיקה bedika and
we have בדיקת חמץ bedikas chametz which is done in the חורין
וסדקין, chorin u'sdakin, right, in the nooks and the crannies. So what
it means is when physically when a בדיקה bedika is done, you
know, the cloth has to be sort of moved around all of
the edges of the vaginal canal, but that's referred to in the
גמרא Gemara as חורין וסדקין chorin u'sdakin right after it referred to
the concept of בית. bayis. So I think there's a very clear
metaphor going on. I think מהומה mehuma was more like rushed. Rushed.
Thank you, that was actually the word I was looking for and
somehow it was escaping me. Thank you very much, that was exactly
the word. Okay, so wait a second, what does this check accomplish
anything? No. So she's trying to check and be good, but we're
not going to trust it enough. Maybe it's good enough also, and
this is an important question I should say, and because it gets
to הלכה halacha questions about what constitutes a בדיקה, bedika, and some
ראשונים rishonim say that there might be different standards for a בדיקה
bedika for טהרה tahara and a בדיקה bedika for the איסור issur
to the husband. And again, the irony is that the איסור issur
to the husband is, you know, of husband and wife having sex
is an איסור כרת, issur kares, right? This stuff is not at
the same level, this טומאה וטהרה. tumah v'tahara. But nevertheless, the טומאה
וטהרה tumah v'tahara world is a world with a lot of stringencies
and a lot of חומרות chumros as we've been seeing and two
checks every single day. So maybe even the, even the mechanics of
the check has a higher standard than it does for the husband.
So according to that, actually is an important, this is an important
גמרא Gemara for the discussion in the ראשונים rishonim of what constitutes
a check nowadays when it's not about טומאה וטהרה. tumah v'tahara. Okay,
so could be that it is good enough for that, or it
could just be she's doing it for herself but it doesn't serve
any הלכה halacha purpose. That's the other. So how far back does
she go in? Until the last time she checked her 24 hours.
That's what made it a good check, right, a real check. Okay,
so because she is rushed, thank you, that was exactly the word,
because she's rushed to be having sex, she's not doing it in
the nooks and crannies and therefore cannot be used, at least for
this. But yes, it's an excellent point. It might be good for
her husband, but it is not good for this. That's a discussion
in the ראשונים. rishonim. תנן, Tnan, now let's look at our משנה.
mishna. המשמשת בעדים הרי זו כפקידה. hamishameshes b'idim harei zu k'pkida. So
a woman who you know had sex with checks, so that they
serve as a check to limit the time. So מאי לאו? mai
lav? So it says בעדים b'idim plural. So what are the two?
מאי לאו חד לפני תשמיש וחד לאחר תשמיש? mai lav chad lifnei
tashmish v'chad l'achar tashmish? Must mean one before sex and one after
sex. So you see therefore that the check before sex was good.
So for this, the גמרא Gemara says לא איידי ואיידי לאחר תשמיש.
lo aidi v'aidi l'achar tashmish. No, two checks after. So what does
it mean? So why two? דאחד לו ואחד לה, d'echad lo v'echad
lah, because she's checking and he's checking. He's wiping himself, she's you
know wiping herself internally and they're both seeing if their cloth has
blood on it afterwards. כדתנן, K'dednan, because if he has blood on
on himself, right, then clearly it came from her. I mean if
it's on, you know, if it's on his genitals then clearly it
came from her. כדתנן דרך בנות ישראל משמשת בשני עדים. k'dednan derech
b'nos yisrael mishameshes b'shnei idim. The because we say it's a משנה
mishna that the practice of Jewish women is to have sex with
two cloths, אחד לו ואחד לה, echad lo v'echad lah, one for
him and one for her, and they're both afterwards. So that's why
it works. It works because we're talking that they did the check
afterwards. But any check if she happened to be doing more than
this and checking before, fine, that's something that she'll do for herself
but it won't be הלכה-ly halacha recognized. So it wasn't an official
תקנה. takana. The תקנה takana of חכמים, Chachamim, we're going to discuss,
we'll see that. Let's see how much it's a practice or a
תקנה. takana. Let's hold off on that, okay? Can it ever come
from him? What? Not, I mean we don't, I mean I guess
it's true, it is possible sometimes men do bleed when they urinate,
but we're assuming not. Anyway, it's not like he has urinated, he's
just ejaculated. Blood? Is there going to be blood in ejaculate? Can
that happen sometimes? Not in a healthy man. Yeah, well, that's... okay,
that's interesting. That's interesting. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says... okay, so
that's external. Right, but he's saying he ejaculated in her and then
it's all mixed up and... oh, I see. Yeah, yeah, right, right,
right. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this: האי מאי? hai
mai? What are you talking about? אי אמרת בשלמא חד לפני תשמיש
וחד לאחר תשמיש, ei amart bishlama chad lifnei tashmish v'chad l'achar tashmish,
if either way... no, no, but if it's his blood she's not
a נידה. niddah. She's not... right, and he's not a זב zav
either. Blood on a man is not זבה. ziva. So, and it
certainly... yeah. So האי מאי? hai mai? אי אמרת בשלמא חד לפני
תשמיש וחד לאחר תשמיש, ei amart bishlama chad lifnei tashmish v'chad l'achar
tashmish, if the two checks is before and after, איצטריך, itztrich, then
we need the משנה mishna to tell me that those checks work
exactly to reject the position you were saying. סלקא דעתך אמינא, salka
da'atach amina, I would have thought מתוך שמהומה לביתה לא בדקה שפיר,
mitoch shemehuma l'veita lo badka shapir, because she's so rushed she wouldn't
have checked well, קא משמע לן ka mashma lan הרי זו כפקידה,
harei zu k'pkida, then the משנה mishna would be telling me that
it is. So if it's talking about the check before, I understand
why the משנה mishna needed to tell me, exactly to you know
contradict your position and say it is a good check. אלא אי
אמרת דאידי ואידי לאחר תשמיש, ela ei amart d'aidi v'aidi l'achar tashmish,
if it's talking about the two checks after, פשיטא, peshita, of course
they're good! Why shouldn't they be good? Why why should that check
be any different than any normal check that she does? So of
course why did the משנה mishna even have to say it? מהו
דתימא Mahu d'teima I might have thought שמא צירה כחרדל shema tzira
k'chardal maybe there's a tiny drop of blood like a mustard seed,
mustard seeds are extremely tiny. So if the drop of blood is
a mustard seed and the semen would cover it, I might have
thought that the check afterwards actually is not a sufficient check to
prove she's טהורה. tehorah. You might have a false negative. Why? Maybe
there's a drop of blood but there's also now a lot of
semen going on, and therefore even though she saw no blood, maybe
it's not a good enough proof. קא משמע לן Kama shma lan
that we do treat it as a good enough proof and we
do say that that stops and you don't go further beyond that.
So now we are saying that the משנה Mishnah says that you
stop. Isn't that obvious? So we're setting two scenarios where it's not
obvious that the check would be good. Either a check before, maybe
she's too rushed, or the check after, maybe the semen is covering
it. But right now we're saying we want to limit it to
the check after and that's the חידוש, chidush, and the check before
we actually want to say does not have that value. Okay, at
least for בעלה, ba'alah, but at least for טהרות. taharos. So the
גמרא Gemara says: אי בעית תימא, Ei ba'is teima, if you want
I'll give you another read of this משנה. Mishnah. שתי בדיקות צריכו
רבנן. Shtei bdikos tzerichu rabbanan. The Rabbis required, and now it goes
from practice to requirement, and now it's going to say both before
and after is a rabbinic requirement. So now every woman not only
has to check twice a day, she also has to check before
and after sex. חד לפני תשמיש וחד אחר תשמיש. Chad lifnei tashmish
v'chad achar tashmish. וכי קתני הרי זה כפקידה על אחר תשמיש. V'chi
katani harei zeh k'pkida, al achar tashmish. And when did it say
that it counts as a good check to stop going backwards? That's
only on the one after. So why does it say המשמשת בעדים
הרי זה כפקידה? Ha'meshameshes b'edim harei zeh k'pkida? So רש"י Rashi and
תוספות Tosafos both say is the way, and it's clear in the
next line of the גמרא, Gemara, the way the גמרא Gemara is
now reading the משנה Mishnah is like this. Not המשמשת בעדים, Ha'meshameshes
b'edim, it says ומשמשת בעדים. U'meshameshes b'edim. It's telling me a requirement.
By the way, a woman has to, you know, use, you know,
do checks when she has sex. And by the way, when she's
doing those checks, הרי זה כפקידה, harei zeh k'pkida, at least one
of them works to stop going backwards. Why the check before-hand then?
To make sure, at least לבעלה, l'ba'alah, to make sure you're not
having sex when you're a נדה. niddah. But it's not going to
be good enough for טהרות. taharos. Right, exactly. וחד אחר תשמיש. V'chad
achar tashmish. וכי קתני הרי זה כפקידה על אחר תשמיש. Chi katani
harei zeh k'pkida al achar tashmish. So there's two things being said
in the משנה. Mishnah. Number one: משמשת בעדים, Meshameshes b'edim, you have
to use them. And number two is: At least one of those
checks works to stop going backwards. So the גמרא Gemara says: המשמשת
קתני, Ha'meshameshes katani, but our משנה Mishnah doesn't say that. It says:
ומשמשת בעדים. U'meshameshes b'edim. It's telling me a requirement. By the way,
a woman has to, you know, use, you know, do checks when
she has sex. And by the way, when she's doing those checks,
הרי זה כפקידה, harei zeh k'pkida, at least one of them works
to stop going backwards. Why the check before-hand then? To make sure,
at least לבעלה, l'ba'alah, to make sure you're not having sex when
you're a נדה. niddah. But it's not going to be good enough
for טהרות. taharos. Right, exactly. וחד אחר תשמיש. V'chad achar tashmish. וכי
קתני הרי זה כפקידה על אחר תשמיש. Chi katani harei zeh k'pkida
al achar tashmish. So there's two things being said in the משנה.
Mishnah. Number one: משמשת בעדים, Meshameshes b'edim, you have to use them.
And number two is: At least one of those checks works to
stop going backwards. So the גמרא Gemara says: המשמשת קתני, Ha'meshameshes katani,
but our משנה Mishnah doesn't say that. It says: And for a
woman who is doing these checks. It's not saying every woman must.
It's saying: In the case of a woman doing these checks. So
the גמרא Gemara says: תני ומשמשת. Tani u'meshameshes. All right, drop the
hey. It's not saying: And for one who is doing these checks,
it's actually becoming a command. A woman must use these and must
do these checks. Now I do want to point out that now
that we're talking actually that it is a rabbinic requirement to do
the checks, and we're still saying it doesn't work for טהרות, taharos,
right, we're saying the check before is rabbinically mandated, not her own
אייגנשקייט. eignshkayt. It's rabbinically mandated to do the check before, nevertheless we're
not going to rely on it for טהרות. taharos. Seems to indicate
that as we were saying before, that there is actually a lower
standard of what's required as a check for the husband than for
טהרות. taharos. Because if the Rabbis are mandating it then it must
serve some function, and if it's not serving the טהרות taharos function,
what function is it serving? At least something to give you enough
confidence to be having sex. So at least for this checking before
sex, it seems that for the husband is a lower standard. Doesn't
mean in other cases like for the שבעה נקיים, shiva neki'im, but
at least for this it does seem to be the case. So
only מן הדין min ha-din was then for him to check too.
That was the rabbinically mandated part. Right, exactly, at least according to
this approach. And by the way, I should also say that both
רש"י Rashi and תוספות Tosafos point out that this line in the
משנה Mishnah comes after it speaks about a דיה שעתה daya sha'atah
by a woman who has a regular וסת. veset. Which means, and
this is again showing, reinforcing what we said before, we would have
been inclined to say if a woman has a regular period, we're
not so concerned about what's going to happen prior, right, to her
when she's expecting her period. Basically she's מוחזקת לטהרה, muchzekes l'tahora, but
we just sort of rejected that before, we actually said no, if
she bleeds she is חושש choshesh 24 hours backwards. And רש"י Rashi
and תוספות Tosafos both point out that this woman who has a
regular period, even when she's having sex during the rest of the
month when it's not her expected period, even she has to check
before and after sex. Just to show you how extreme it was
in this time of טומאה וטהרה. tumah v'taharah. Every woman, twice a
day, even at the time you're not expecting your period, plus before
and after sex, even if you're not expecting your period, every woman
is doing those checks. Okay, now move on. Can she double duty?
Double duty, woman checking after, and at the end of the day?
Doesn't sound like it. I mean I guess if you exactly time
it correctly you're close enough. ממעטת את היד Mema'etes es hayad מעת
לעת. me'eis le'eis. So it says these checks before and after sex
limit the time going back of 24 hours until the last check.
So the גמרא Gemara says: השתא מעת לעת ממעטת פקידה לפקידה מבעיא?
Hashta me'eis le'eis mema'etes, pkida l'pkida mi'baya? If it limits the 24
hours, it certainly limits the פקידה לפקידה. pkida l'pkida. Now what's the
קל וחומר? kal v'chomer? Anyway, so תוספות Tosafos explains the קל וחומר
kal v'chomer is the only reason we'd have to go back 24
hours is... this woman has not done what she's supposed to. She's
been irresponsible, hasn't checked twice a day. So if we're going to
use this check around sex to even help us in a case
where she's been negligent, certainly it will help us in a case
where she's done what she's supposed to and she's been checking regularly
and it will shrink the time even further. So the גמרא Gemara
says not necessarily. מהו דתימא, mahu d'teima, I might have thought, מעת
לעת קבעו רבנן לפסידא דטהרות. me'eis le'eis katchu rabanan l'psayday taharos. If
you're going to have to go back 24 hours, then maybe there's
going to be a lot of things that could have become טמא
tamei in the last 24 hours. So to protect all of those
things, we're going to use even this check, even this check which
we indicated might not be 100 percent. אבל מפקידה לפקידה, aval mip'kidah
lip'kidah, but if all you're going to be doing is going back
to the last time you checked, so there's not so much at
stake, and if there's not so much at stake לא, lo, maybe
we won't allow it to be limited by this check around sex,
קא משמע לן kamashma lan that even there we will. Why is
the check around sex less valid? Like we said before, if it's
the one before, because she's rushed, although we said that that's actually
isn't valid. So even if it's the one after, there's the question
about semen covering it over. So therefore maybe we would not have
relied on it in all cases and it's telling us we do
rely on it. Okay. כיצד דייה שעתה. kaytzad daya sha'atah. How is
it that she only goes by the moment she finds it? So
it spoke about her being on a bed, getting up from the
bed, there's blood on the bed, that was a case of ראייה,
re'iyah, not a כתם, ketem, and therefore she's טמאה, tmei'ah, but the
טהרות taharos that she's been doing prior are not, because this is
a woman who saw it during her period. Okay. So גמרא Gemara
says זמני ליה למיתני היושבת במטה ועסוקה בטהרות? zaminei lei lemisnei hayoshevet
b'mitah va'asukah b'taharos? Why did it have to give me this scenario
of sitting on a bed? Just say she was, I don't know,
doing טהרות. taharos. למיתני היושבת ועסוקה בטהרות ופירשה וראתה. lemisnei hayoshevet va'asukah
b'taharos upirshah v'ra'asah. Just say she was doing טהרות taharos and then
after she finished, she saw that she was bleeding. הא קא משמע
לן טעמא דדייה שעתה. ha kamashma lan ta'ama d'daya sha'atah. No, because
it's telling me a principle. That the reason she's טמאה tmei'ah and
it's טהור tahor is because she's a דייה שעתה. daya sha'atah. We
assume it just happened now. הא מעת לעת, ha me'eis le'eis, if
it would have been a woman that it didn't happen בשעת וסתה
b'sha'as vestah or a woman that did not have a וסת veset
and we would go back 24 hours, not only would the טהרות
taharos be טמאים, tmei'im, the grain and the flour she was doing,
but מטה נמי מטמיא, mitah nami mitamya, the bed also would be
טמא. tamei. Okay, we wanted to give you a scenario of a
bed to indicate that there's other things at stake here, not only
are the טהרות taharos at stake but the status of the bed.
And if we're saying from here on in then everything is safe:
the bed, the טהרות, taharos, etc. But if we said retroactively, the
טהרות taharos would be טמא tamei and the bed would be טמא
tamei now. Isn't that obvious? Why should the bed be different than
the flour and the grain? So here's why it's not obvious. מסייע
ליה לזעירי. misayay lei l'Zeiri. This supports זעירי, Zeiri, דאמר זעירי מעת
לעת שבנדה עושה משכב ומושב לטמא אדם ולטמא בגדים. d'amar Zeiri me'eis
le'eis she'b'niddah osah mishkav umoshav l'tamei adam u'l'tamei begadim. So you may
know, a נדה niddah is an אב הטומאה, av hatumah, which is
an אם הטומאה, aim hatumah, which we should take over... an אב
הטומאה, av hatumah, and which means the way it works is, anything
she touches, person, food, vessels, is טמא, tamei, they become a ראשון.
rishon. But the only thing that the person or whatever or the
vessels can touch now, the one-degree derivative, the only thing that can
be a second-degree derivative, a שני, sheni, is food. Okay, so that's
the normal story. So she touches a chair or a person, whatever,
it's a ראשון rishon and it can only be מטמא mitamei food.
But if she sits on a chair, the Torah says that there's
a special הלכה, halakhah, she's יושבת בתורה, yoshevet b'Torah, that her משכב,
mishkav, her seat or the thing she lies on, is considered an
אב הטומאה. av hatumah. It's not considered a derivative, it's considered itself
a source and it's מטמא אדם וכלים, mitamei adam v'kelim, like a
normal אב הטומאה. av hatumah. So here's the question: like her. When
we are going to say she's טמאה tmei'ah retroactively 24 hours, are
we going to apply in the last 24 hours, since it's all
rabbinic as we've said, all of the הלכות halakhos of נדה? niddah?
And if she sat on something in the last 24 hours, are
we going to treat it as a משכב ומושב mishkav u'moshav and
as an אב הטומאה? av hatumah? So here we're saying yes, that's
why our משנה Mishnah mentioned that she was on a bed to
indicate to you that the bed could be as soon as she's
a נדה, niddah, you're thinking משכב, mishkav, and to indicate to you
that the bed could get that status of משכב mishkav when you
are מטמא mitamei her retroactively. Okay, that's how we're reading the משנה.
Mishnah. I mean back then things, seriously, it was not a hygienic
society. That's why you checked twice a day, so you limit your
exposure. You can't sit on anything, you can't use the same utensils.
I know, you limit your exposure. It touches everything: chairs, couches. All
right. You understand why there'd be a really good reason to פוסק
pasken that וסת קבוע שלא בשעת וסתה veset kavua she'lo b'sha'as vestah
is מסולקת דמים. mesuleket damim. But yeah, that is exactly it, that's
why we're doing all these checks to try to limit the exposure.
Okay, so let's read that again. טעמא דדייה הא מעת לעת מטה
נמי מטמיא, ta'ama d'daya ha me'eis le'eis mitah nami mitamya, it's טמא
tamei as a מטה. mitah. מסייע ליה לזעירי דאמר זעירי מעת לעת
שבנדה, misayay lei l'Zeiri d'amar Zeiri me'eis le'eis she'b'niddah, going back 24
hours of נדה, niddah, עושה משכב ומושב, osah mishkav umoshav, it's a
full משכב ומושב, mishkav u'moshav, לטמא אדם ולטמא בגדים, l'tamei adam u'l'tamei
begadim, to make a person טמא tamei and clothes טמא. tamei. By
the way, לטמא אדם לטמא בגדים l'tamei adam l'tamei begadim means something
more, I should say. It means that there's a special sometimes the
הלכה halakhah is is that not only are you טמא tamei but
the clothes on you are טמא tamei and not because they're touching
you, but because they're considered one with you. That's not always the
case, it depends on the טומאה tumah and the form of contact.
But basically, if I were to touch a משכב mishkav of a
נידה, niddah, I would be a ראשון rishon and my clothes would
be a ראשון, rishon, right? Because my clothes didn't touch, they're only
touching me, so they should be nothing. My clothes can't become a
שני, sheni, but no, the הלכה halacha of a משכב mishkav is
that the person and the clothes he's wearing all become a ראשון
rishon with him. That's the לטמא אדם ולטמא בגדים. litamei adam ulitamei
bgadim. No, just clothes you're wearing. Okay. So now the גמרא gemara
says one minute, I've got a question about this. Not clear. האי
מיטה דלית בה דעת לישאל הוא. Hai mita d'leis bei daas lishoel
hu. We're going back to that. This bed is something that you
can't ask whether it became טמא. tamei. וכל דבר שאין בו דעת
לישאל ספיקו טהור. V'chol davar she'ein bo daas lishoel sefeko tahor. And
anything and any טומאה טהרה tumah taharah question, if it's about a
thing that can't be asked, it's טהור. tahor. Now of course the
question is the grain she was dealing with can't be asked. So
here yes, but at least she was holding the grain and we're
assuming that if she's holding it, handling it, then it becomes like
one... it's considered an extension of her, and since obviously you can
ask her, so right. But the bed, which she wasn't holding and
handling, that should since you can't ask it, it should be טהור.
tahor. So the גמרא gemara says תרגמה זעירי דשחברותיה נושאות אותה במיטה,
targuma Zeiri deshechaverteha nosot osa bamita, דהוה ליה יד חברותיה. dehavaleh yad
chaverteha. The same way we assumed before he's handling it, it becomes
an extension of her. If her friends are carrying her by lifting
up a bed and transporting her from one place to another, and
maybe she's sick, who knows what, then because you can ask her
friends, there יש בו דעת לישאל yesh bo daas lishoel and they're
carrying the bed, therefore it's considered an extension of them and therefore
it's considered יש בו דעת לישאל. yesh bo daas lishoel. Okay, תוספות
Tosafos says also, תוספות Tosafos also adds the fact that the friends
would become טמא tamei for carrying a נידה, niddah, so it also
directly her status directly impacts their status as well, not just the
bed's status and so on. But everything... no. But now we're going
to qualify that. Let's just finish this point. והשתא דאמר רבי יוחנן,
vehashta de’amar Rabi Yochanan, now that רבי יוחנן Rabi Yochanan says ספק
טומאה הבאה בידי אדם נשאלין עליה אפילו בכלי מונח על גבי קרקע,
safek tumah habaa bidei adam nishalin aleha afilu bicheli munach al gabi
karka, that redefines the question about יש בו דעת לישאל. yesh bo
daas lishoel. If there's a doubt of טומאה tumah but it's coming
through human agency, meaning we're assuming יש בו דעת לישאל yesh bo
daas lishoel means by the object becoming טמא, tamei, can that be
asked? But now he's saying no, even the person transmitting the טומאה,
tumah, right? There's always two, there's the one transmitting and receiving. We
were assuming it goes by the recipient of the טומאה. tumah. But
he says a טומאה tumah that comes through a person, even as
the transmitter, even if it relates to a vessel on the ground,
that is like to me יש בו דעת לישאל. yesh bo daas
lishoel. That's like the recipient could be asked, אף על פי af
al pi so therefore and therefore it's טמא. tamei. We we consider
that a יש בו דעת לישאל. yesh bo daas lishoel. So once
that's true, now we can say אף על פי שאין חברותיה נושאות
אותה במיטה. af al pi she'ein chaverteha nosot osa bamita. Now we
can say even if her friends are not carrying her, we are
we can say because the הלכה... halacha... now this is the basic
question. When we say it's only but where somebody can be asked,
which somebody? The somebody bringing about the טומאה tumah or does it
have to be the somebody becoming טמא? tamei? So we were assuming
the somebody becoming טמא, tamei, which would radically limit the cases when
we would say ספק טומאה טמא. safek tumah tamei. Now we're saying
no no no, as even if the person is transmitting the טומאה,
tumah, that's יש בו דעת לישאל yesh bo daas lishoel and ספק
טמא. safek tamei. So what's a scenario אין בו דעת לישאל? ein
bo daas lishoel? That would be something like we had yesterday. You
left a loaf of bread on a shelf and a טמא tamei
garment on the bottom and you left the room and you came
back and it was on the floor. No human was involved in
that process, right? No humans were hurt, no animals were hurt in
the making of this. But if a human was involved in the
process at any stage, then it's יש בו דעת לישאל yesh bo
daas lishoel and טמא tamei and we'll pick up with this tomorrow.